为什么不按下AZ-5按钮
Why didn't you press the AZ-5 button?
我们按了  就在那时发生了爆炸
We did. And that's when it exploded.
切尔诺贝利
前情提要
我不希望我的人在这儿多待一秒
I don't want my men here one more second than they need to be.
要是这东西有用  你就戴着了
If these worked, you'd be wearing them.
瓦西里
Vasily...
我们要有孩子了
We're gonna have a baby.
你明不明白现在面临的状况
Do you have any idea what you're dealing with?
人们会知道的
People are going to hear.
所有人会知道什么
What is everyone gonna hear?
任何可能性都要追查下去
We have to pursue every possibility,
不管到底是谁的错
no matter who is to blame.
这整个区域必须全面疏散
This entire region must be completely evacuated.
需要多少人手
How many men do you require?
大约需要75万人
Approximately 750,000 men.
原创翻译  双语字幕
最新连载海外影视剧下载
请登陆 www.YYeTs.com
仅供交流学习  禁止商用盈利
翻译     草草  苏小黛  Eunice  elingbow  哈里不是波特
翻译     马丁马丁回音山  tong大梨  Sakura的小书包
翻译     小胖橘子  白夜君  放开那个方丈  小酸奶
顾问     elingbow
校对     草草  苏葵
时间轴     荞麦麦  Caroline
后期     拉图
总监     苏葵
该走了
It's time to go.
你听到没有
Did you hear me?
这是在撤离  你明白吗
This is an evacuation. You understand?
你必须跟我走
You have to come with me.
为什么
Why?
因为他们下命令了  现在我来转告你
Because they told me, so now I'm telling you.
村里所有人都得走
Everyone in this village, everyone.
这里不安全  空气中有辐射
It's not safe here. There's radiation in the air.
你是什么毛病
What's wrong with you?
你知道我多老了吗
Do you know how old I am?
我不知道  很老吧
I don't know. Old.
我82了
I'm 82.
我一辈子都住在这里
I've lived here my whole life.
就在这里  那栋房子  就这地方
Right here, that house, this place.
我管安全不安全的呢
What do I care about safe?
我有任务  别给我找麻烦
I have a job. Don't cause trouble.
麻烦
Trouble?
你不是第一个扛枪站在这里的士兵
You're not the first soldier to stand here with a gun.
我12岁时  革命开始了
When I was 12, the revolution came.
沙皇的士兵  然后是布尔什维克
Czar's men. Then Bolsheviks.
就像你这样的男孩  列队前进
Boys like you marching in lines.
他们叫我们走  我不
They told us to leave. No.
然后是斯大林和他的饥荒
Then there was Stalin and his famine,
乌克兰大饥荒
the Holodomor.
我父母死了  两个姐妹死了
My parents died. Two of my sisters died.
他们叫我们剩下的人走
They told the rest of us to leave.
我不
No.
然后二战爆发了
Then the Great War.
德国人  俄罗斯人
German boys. Russian boys.
更多的士兵  饥荒和死尸
More soldiers, more famine, more bodies.
我的兄弟们一去不回
My brothers never came home.
但我留下了  我现在还在这里
But I stayed, and I'm still here.
我见识了那么多
After all that I have seen...
难道要现在走吗
so I should leave now,
就因为我根本看不到的东西
because of something I cannot see at all?
我不
No.
等一下
Just one moment!
该走了
It's time to go.
请站起来
Please stand up now.
这是你最后的警告
This is your last warning.
该走了
It's time to go.
切尔诺贝利
第四集
乌克兰苏维埃共和国  基辅
1986年8月  爆炸发生四个月后
来吧
Come on.
.4
Point four.
.6
Point six.
Fifteen.
普里皮亚季
切尔诺贝利隔离区
我是列加索夫
Legasov.
我去那边跟他碰头
I'll meet him there.
原子令人敬畏
The atom is a humbling thing.
不是令人敬畏  是让人羞愧
It's not humbling, it's humiliating.
为什么堆芯仍然暴露在空气中
Why is the core still exposed to the air?
为什么我们还没把它掩盖起来
Why have we not already covered it up?
我们也想  但我们无法靠得足够近
We want to, but we can't get close enough.
屋顶的碎片是堆芯喷出来的石墨
The debris on the roof is graphite from the core itself.
如果不把它从屋顶推下去  到反应堆里
Until we can push it off the roof back into the reactor,
任何靠近的人都会死
it'll kill anyone who gets near it.
你可以看到屋顶有三层
You can see the roof is in three levels.
我们给它们起了名字  小的这层叫卡缇娅
We've named them-- the small one here is Katya.
每小时一千伦琴
One thousand roentgen per hour.
预计暴露其中两小时就足以致命
Presume two hours of exposure is fatal.
边上那层叫妮娜
The one on the side-- Nina.
每小时两千伦琴  暴露一小时就可致命
Two thousand roentgen. One hour, fatal.
我们在阿富汗用过遥控推土机
We used remote-controlled bulldozers in Afghanistan.
太重了  会直接掉进去
Too heavy. They'd fall right through.
-那...  -月球车
- So then...? - Moon rovers.
月球步行者STR-1  那种很轻
Lunokhod STR-1's. They're light.
如果在上面铺上铅  它们能承受住辐射
And if we line them with lead, they can withstand the radiation.
我们当初没能把人送上月球
We couldn't put a man on the moon.
至少现在可以不让他们上楼顶送命
At least we can keep a man off a roof.
那是最关键的  大将
That is the most important thing, General.
无论如何  人都不能上去
Under no circumstances can men go up there.
只能用机器人
Robots only.
这里这一大片区域呢
What about this large section here?
玛莎
Masha.
每小时一万两千伦琴
Twelve thousand roentgen.
如果从头到脚
If you were to stand there in
穿着全套防护装备站在那里两分钟
full protective gear head-to-toe for two minutes,
寿命就会减半
your life expectancy would be cut in half.
站三分钟  会在几个月内死亡
By three minutes, you're dead within months.
哪怕是我们的月球车也无法在玛莎上运作
Even our lunar rovers won't work on Masha.
如此大剂量的伽马射线能穿透一切
That amount of gamma radiation penetrates everything.
粒子会直接
The particles literally
粉碎微芯中的电路
shred the circuits in microchips apart.
如果它比电灯开关更复杂
If it's more complicated than a light switch,
玛莎会直接毁了它
Masha will destroy it.
可以这么说
It would be fair to say that
那屋顶是地球上最危险的地方
that piece of roof is the most dangerous place on Earth.
那么...我们该怎么做
So... what do we do?
我们也想问你这个问题
That's what we wanted to ask you.
这是181号帐篷吗
Tent 181?
没事  不要钱
It's all right. It's free.
现在喝酒早了点
It's a little early.
我叫巴乔
Bacho.
帕沃
Pavel.
是吗
Yeah?
你之前在哪支部队
What unit were you in?
他们派我去了基辅的车辆调配场
Uh, they had me in motor pool in Kiev,
-但之后他们...  -不是说这个
- but then they-- - Not this bullshit.
在阿富汗哪儿驻军
In Afghanistan.
我没去阿富汗
Oh, um, I wasn't in Afghanistan.
我不是军人
I'm not in the military.
他们人手不够了
They're running out of men.
淋浴  食物
Showers. Food.
这些人负责负责挖地
Those guys, they dig up the ground.
那些则负责砍树
Those guys, they cut down trees.
那些人好像负责疏散
Those guys, they evacuate people, I think,
比如村民
like villagers.
那他们呢
What about them?
我不认识他们  去他们的
I don't know them. Fuck them.
雅尼克
Janek!
-干吗  -给我护裆套
- What do you want? - Give me an egg basket.
-不行  我只有一个  -快他妈给我
- No, I've only got the one-- - Give me the fucking basket!
我罩着他  明白了吗
He's with me, you understand?
谁都不准惹他
Nobody fucks with him.
这是我们用铅废料做的
We make these from lead scrap.
-穿上  兜着你的蛋  -现在吗
- Put it on under your balls. - Now?
不  你可以等到辐射给你烧个逼出来再穿
No, no. You can wait until the radiation gives you a cunt.
当然是现在
Yes, now.
穿在衣服外面  蠢逼
Over your clothes. Fucking shit.
-你打过猎吗  -没有
- You ever go hunting? - No.
今天你走运了
Well... today's your lucky day.
你  我  还有帐篷里那亚美尼亚丑逼伽罗
You, me, that ugly Armenian in the tent, Garo,
今天负责动物管制
we do animal control.
动物管制
Animal control?
对  它们有辐射
Yeah, they're radioactive,
所以必须杀死
so they have to go.
但难度不大  它们多数是宠物
But it's not hard. They're mostly pets.
看到你会很高兴  屁颠冲你跑来
They're happy to see you. They run right up to you.
砰
Bang!
你把尸体搬上卡车
You load the bodies on the truck,
丢进坑里  用混凝土埋起来
dump them in a pit, bury them in concrete.
然后我们喝酒
And then we drink.
想喝多少伏特加都行  外加一千卢布
As much vodka as you want, plus a thousand rubles.
来  我给你找把枪
Let's go get you a gun.
莫斯科莱蒙诺索夫大学图书馆
什么事
Yes?
我要看这些文件
I need to see the following documents.
但需要经过批准
They're listed as permission only.
我为中央委员会工作
I'm working for the Central Committee.
同志
Comrade?
她可以看这个
She can have that one.
谢谢  同志
Thank you, Comrade.
安全
All clear.
开启摄影机
Bring up the cameras.
-信号怎么样  -可以接受
- Signal? - Acceptable.
正在进行机载诊断
Running onboard diagnostics.
可以移动时告诉我
Tell me when we're ready to move it.
想想这可是月球上用的机器
To think that's what we put on the moon.
不是那台
Well, not that one.
我知道不是那一台
I know not that one.
这台月球车在仓库里  他们可以再造两台
This rover was in storage. They can build two more.
妮娜和卡缇娅够用了
That should cover Nina and Katya.
玛莎呢
And Masha?
中央委员会通知我
The Central Committee have informed me
他们有可能找到了
that they may have found something
能在那层用的机器  国外找的
that could work up there. From the outside.
美国货
American?
当然不是
Of course not.
是德国警用机器人
It's a German police robot.
西德  所以可想而知
West German, so, as you can imagine,
和他们交涉并不容易
that wasn't an easy conversation to have.
诊断完成
Diagnostics complete.
准备启动总电源与电机
Ready to engage main power and motor.
开始
Begin.
可以移动吗
Can we move it?
瓦列利  怎么  你在笑吗
Valery, what's that? A smile?
看来你的病情有所好转  迪亚特洛夫同志
I see your condition has improved, Comrade Dyatlov.
不  出去
No. Leave.
我需要你的帮助
I need your help.
阿基莫夫按下了AZ-5
Akimov initiated AZ-5.
-当你下达指令时  -指令  什么指令
- When you gave the order-- - Order? What order?
托普特诺夫下令  阿基莫夫执行
Toptunov called it out, Akimov pressed it.
这是他们唯一的正确决定
It was the only good decision they made.
那些无能的蠢货
Incompetent morons.
你能否确认反应堆爆炸
Can you confirm that the reactor exploded
发生在他们执行停堆操作之后
after they attempted to shut it down?
我怎么知道它爆炸了
How do I even know it exploded, huh?
这是我在国家档案馆里找到的
I found this in the state archive.
1976年写的
Written in 1976.
是关于RBMK反应堆
It's about the operation
在极端条件下操作的论文
of RBMK reactors under extreme conditions.
那又如何
So?
作者们的名字被抹掉了
The names of the authors have been redacted,
还有两页也被撕掉了
and two pages have been removed.
国家必须保守自己的机密  同志
Well, the State must protect its secrets, Comrade.
你敢有不同的意见吗
Do you dare suggest otherwise?
他们犯了个错误
They made a mistake.
他们没有修改目录
They didn't redact the table of contents.
缺失的两页明显是有关
The missing pages apparently refer
正空泡系数和AZ-5的内容
to a positive void coefficient and AZ-5.
这对你来说有什么意义吗
Does that mean anything to you?
你的目的是什么  你为什么问我这个
What are you after here? Why are you asking me this?
你在反应堆工作  你比我更了解它
You worked with the reactor. You know it better than I do.
那都是我的错了
So everything's my fault, then?
就是这个目的吧
Is that what this is?
我不是来指责你的
I'm not here to blame you.
我是来弄清楚到底发生了什么
I'm here to find out what happened.
不管你是否意识到了
And whether you realize it or not,
我是最可能让你免遭枪毙的人
I'm your best chance to avoid a bullet.
你到底能不能帮我
Can you help me or not?
我不知道这里写了什么
I have no idea what would've gone here.
空泡系数和AZ-5没有任何关系
Void coefficients have nothing to do with AZ-5.
行了  你可以走了
There. Now you can go.
-你一点都不好奇吗  -有什么意义呢
- You're not even curious? - What for?
你觉得问对了问题就能得到真相吗
You think the right question will get you the truth?
根本没有真相
There is no truth.
随你怎么去问上级  得到的只有谎言
Ask the bosses whatever you want and you'll get the lie.
而我还是会吃枪子
And I will get the bullet.
我只有两个规矩
I only have two rules.
第一
One.
不要拿枪对着我  这个很简单  对吧
Don't point this gun at me. That's easy, right?
你可以拿枪对着那个蠢货
You can point it at this piece of shit.
我根本无所谓  但不能对着我
I don't give a fuck. Never me.
第二
Two.
如果你打了个动物  而它没有死
If you hit an animal and it doesn't die,
继续射击直到它死了
keep shooting until it does.
不许让它们受罪  否则我就杀了你
Don't let them suffer, or I'll kill you.
明白了吗
Understand?
我是认真的
I mean it.
我杀过很多人
I've killed a lot of people.
很好  那我们就准备好了
Good. Then we're ready.
一旦我们开始
Once we start,
它们就会跑去自己觉得安全的房子
they'll run inside where they feel safe.
我们挨家挨户搜
So we go door-to-door.
知道了吗
Okay?
很好
Good.
干活去  挨家挨户搜
Do your job. Door-to-door.
走开  快走
Go. Go.
快走  让你快走
Go away. Go!
不许让它们受罪
Don't let them suffer.
抱歉  对不起
Sorry. Sorry.
你把它拖到卡车那儿去
You're dragging that to the truck.
你要吃点东西吗
You gonna eat?
喝了
Drink.
再喝一口
Again.
听着
Look...
每个人第一次都这样
This happens to everyone their first time.
通常是第一次杀人的时候
Normally when you kill a man.
但对你而言  是一条狗
But for you, a dog.
那又如何  没什么好羞愧的
So what? There's no shame in it.
你还记得你的第一次吗  伽罗
You remember your first time, Garo?
我的第一次  是在阿富汗
My first time-- Afghanistan.
我们正在穿过一栋房子
We were moving through a house,
突然出现了一个人  我射中他的腹部
and suddenly a man was there and I shot him in the stomach.
这是真实的战争故事
Yeah, that's a real war story.
绝不是电影里拍的那样美好
They're never any good stories like in the movies.
都是些破事儿
They're shit.
一个人站在那儿  砰  打中腹部
A man was there-- boom, stomach.
我很害怕  那天接下来的时间里
I was so scared. I didn't pull the trigger again
我再也没扣动扳机
for the rest of the day.
我就想  "就这样了  巴乔
I thought, "Well, that's it, Bacho.
你开枪打中了人
"You put a bullet in someone.
你不再是原来的你了
"You're not you anymore.
你已经回不去了"
You'll never be you again."
然而第二天早晨醒来
But then you wake up the next morning,
你还是那个你
and you're still you.
接着你就意识到
And you realize...
一直以来你都是这样的人
that was you all along.
只是之前你不知道
You just didn't know.
全人类的幸福
The happiness of all mankind.
什么
What?
"我们的目标为了全人类的幸福"
"Our goal is the happiness of all mankind."
为了全人类的幸福
是啊
Yeah.
我很幸福
I'm happy.
我每天都很幸福
I'm happy every day.
好了  回去工作
All right. Back to work.
走吧
Come on.
1986年9月
到了
It's here.
好了
All right.
过来
Get over.
好  抓住
Right. Hang on.
慢点  小心
Easy now. Careful.
拿住
Hold it!
小丑
Joker.
德国人给它起的名字  "小丑"
It's what the Germans named it: "Joker."
-准备好了吗  -准备好了
- Is it ready? - It's ready.
小丑
信号良好
Good signal.
摄像头
Cameras.
电机
Motors.
电机良好  信号良好
Motors, good. Signals, good.
好了  我们慢点来
All right, let's take this easy.
前进一米  倒退一米
Forward one meter, reverse one meter.
前进一米
Forward one.
德国人
Germans.
后退一米
Reverse one.
信号中断了吗
Did you lose the signal?
不是信号的问题  是车
It's not the signal. It's the vehicle.
它坏了
It's dead.
操
Shit.
我当然知道他们在听
Of course I know they're listening!
我想让他们听见  我想让他们全都听见
I want them to hear! I want them to hear it all!
你知道我们在这干什么吗
Do you know what we're doing here?!
告诉那些天才他们都干了什么
Tell those geniuses what they have done!
我他妈不在乎
I don't give a fuck!
告诉他们  去告诉他们  雷日科夫
Tell them! Go tell them! Ryzhkov!
告诉他们他就是个笑话
Go tell them he's a joke!
告诉狗屁戈尔巴乔夫
Tell fucking Gorbachev!
告诉他们
Tell them!
国家的官方立场是
The official position of the State
苏联是不会发生
is that a global nuclear catastrophe
全球性灾难事故的
is not possible in the Soviet Union.
他们告诉德国人
They told the Germans that
检测到的最高辐射值是两千伦琴
the highest detected level of radiation was 2,000 roentgen.
他们给出的是对外宣称的数值
They gave them the propaganda number.
那个机器人本就没用
That robot was never going to work.
我们需要一台新电话
We need a new phone.
如果我们不清理呢
What if we don't clear it?
我们必须清理
We have to clear it.
如果不清理屋顶  就不能在它外面建外壳
If we don't clear the roof, we can't build a cover over it.
如果不用石棺覆盖  那就是一万两千伦琴
If we can't cover it, that's 12,000 roentgen.
几乎两倍的广岛原子弹辐射量
That's nearly twice the radiation from the Hiroshima bomb.
-而且是每小时  源源不断  -我知道
- Every hour, hour after-- - I know, I know, I know.
用铅怎么样
What about lead?
我们也许可以
We could-- I don't know.
可以把熔化的铅从空中倒下来  像涂层一样
We could melt it and pour it from above, like a coating.
首先  我们手头的铅已经快用完了
First of all, we've already used most of the lead we had--
-为了裹住  -其他反应堆厂房的仪器上
- to line the... - There's lead sheeting around the instruments
还有铅层
in the other reactor buildings.
士兵们正剥下来  用在防护服上
The soldiers are stripping it for their armor.
你是认真的吗
Are you serious?
即使可以  我们还得把熔化的金属放在直升机里
Even if, we're still talking about boiling metal in a helicopter.
这可是铅  鲍里斯  重得很
And it's lead, Boris, it'll weight a ton.
把石墨射进洞里怎么样
What if we shoot the graphite into the hole?
我们有大口径的子弹  爆炸子弹
We've got high-caliber bullets, exploding bullets.
这种子弹不会反弹  而是会推动
They wouldn't just ricochet, they'd push--
你想往暴露在外的核反应堆
You wanna shoot exploding bullets
射爆炸子弹
at an exposed nuclear reactor?
-这个嘛  -不不
- Well... - No, no.
我们再去把楼顶点着火吧
Let's go light that roof back on fire.
第一次扑灭得太轻松了
It was so easy to put out the first time.
我们到底在说什么
What are we talking about here?
我们需要新的机器人
We need another robot.
一台可以承受辐射的机器人
One that can withstand the radiation.
我问过了  没有这样的机器人
I've asked. There is nothing.
美国货呢
The Americans?
如果美国有这种科技
If the Americans had that kind of technology,
你觉得他们会给我们吗
do you really think they'd give it to us?
即使他们真的有
And even if they would,
中央委员会也不会屈膝请求
the Central Committee will never stoop to ask.
你我都心知肚明
You know it, I know it.
没有机器人
There are no robots.
生物机器人
Biorobots.
这是什么
What was that?
我们用生物机器人
We use biorobots.
也就是人
Men.
今天碰见了很多
A lot today.
它们从哪找到食物的
Where do they get their food?
它们吃鸡
They eat the chickens.
然后互相吞食
Then they eat each other.
挨家挨户搜
Door-to-door.
帕沃
Pavel?
Pavel!
你听不到吗  我在跟你说话
You don't hear me? I'm talking to you.
妈的
Fuck.
你出去吧
Just go outside.
去吧
Go.
1986年10月
士兵同志们
Comrade soldiers,
苏维埃人民已经受够了这场事故
the Soviet people have had enough of this accident.
他们希望我们收拾好残局
They want us to clean this up,
我们将这项艰巨的任务托付于你们
and we have entrusted you with this serious task.
鉴于作业区域的性质
Because of the nature of the working area,
你们每人只有不到90秒的时间进行作业
you will each have no more than 90 seconds to solve this problem.
认真听好我的每一条指示
Listen carefully to each of my instructions,
并严格服从
and do exactly as you have been told.
这是为了你自身安全  以及你战友的安全
This is for your own safety and the safety of your comrades.
你们要进入3号反应堆厂房
You will enter Reactor Building Three,
上楼后不要直接前往屋顶
climb the stairs but do not immediately proceed to the roof.
到达顶楼后  先在室内等候
When you get to the top, wait inside,
在去往屋顶的入口处喘口气
behind the entrance to the roof and catch your breath.
为后续的工作做好准备
You will need it for what comes next.
这里是作业区域  我们必须将石墨清理干净
This is the working area. We must clear the graphite.
有些石墨成块状
Some of it is in blocks,
重量大约四十到五十公斤
weighing approximately 40 to 50 kilograms.
必须将它们从屋顶这边投下
They all must be thrown over the edge here.
看你们的同志们正快速通过入口
Watch your comrades moving fast from this opening,
之后左转
then turning to the left,
进入作业区域
and entering the workspace here.
小心不要绊倒
Take care not to stumble.
屋顶上有个洞  小心不要掉进去
There's a hole in the roof. Take care not to fall.
务必快速行动
You will need to move quickly,
万分小心
and you will need to move carefully.
听完我的描述  清楚你们的任务了吗
Do you understand your mission as I have described it?
是的  大将同志
Yes, Comrade General.
这是你们人生中最重要的90秒
These are the most important 90 seconds of your lives.
将任务牢记于心  然后着手工作
Commit your task to memory, then do your job.
该出发了  90秒之后  我会拉响警铃
It's time to go. After 90 seconds, I will ring a bell.
听到铃声  你们立刻返回
When you hear it, return immediately,
将铲子丢进垃圾桶
drop your shovels in the bin,
沿走廊一直走去进行消毒
and proceed down the hallway for decontamination.
最重要的是  在屋顶时
Above all, while on the roof,
将残骸扔出护栏
throw your debris over the rail.
不要向护栏外看  明白没有
Do not look over the rail. Is that clear?
非常好
Very well.
听我口令  准备  出发
On my mark. Ready. Go.
士兵同志们
Comrade soldier.
你的任务完成了
You're done.
该走了
Time to go.
你的手套
Your glove!
妈妈  妈妈
Mommy! Mommy!
普里皮亚季
1986年12月
抱歉让你来这
I'm sorry for all this.
但我们需要和你谈谈  而且没有...
But we needed to speak to you somewhere without...
他们要审判迪亚特洛夫
They're going to put Dyatlov on trial,
还有布卡诺夫和福明
and Bryukhanov and Fomin.
我们会被传唤  作为专家证人
We're going to be asked to give expert testimony,
我们三个都要
all three of us.
但这是...在庭审之前
But that's-- Before that happens--
中央委员会让列加索夫去维也纳
The Central Committee is sending Legasov to Vienna.
那是国际原...
It's the headquarters of the International--
国际原子能机构的总部
Atomic Energy Agency.
是的  这我知道
Yeah, I know what's in Vienna.
他们让你干什么
What are they asking you to do?
告诉全世界发生了什么
Tell the world what happened.
那你最好知道发生了什么
Well, then you better know what happened.
我构建了一条时间线
I've constructed a timeline,
以每分钟为单位
minute by minute.
有的地方以秒为单位
Second by second in some places.
每一项决定  按下的每一个按钮
Every decision, every button push,
开关的每一次通断
every turn of a switch.
然后呢  他们有罪吗
And? Are they guilty?
是的
Yes.
严重失职  违反安全规定
Of gross incompetence, violation of safety regulations,
他们的鲁莽简直难以置信
recklessness beyond belief.
但是爆炸呢  我不确定
But the explosion? I'm not sure.
什么叫你不确定
What do you mean you're not sure?
我分析了数据
I've analyzed the data.
托普特诺夫说的是实话
Toptunov was telling the truth.
他们关闭了反应堆  然后就爆炸了
They shut the reactor down, and then it exploded.
我觉得这篇文章可能会有答案
I think this article may have the answer,
但其中的两页被人撕了
but two pages have been removed.
你之前看过这个
You've seen this before.
请相信我这话
Please, believe me when I tell you that
我真不知道这会导致爆炸
I had no idea it could cause an explosion.
-我们当时都不知道  -你们都不知道什么
- None of us knew. - None of you knew what?
1975年  列宁格勒的一座RBMK反应堆
In 1975, in an RBMK reactor in Leningrad,
一条燃料管道破裂
a fuel channel ruptured.
操作员按下AZ-5按钮
The operators pressed AZ-5,
但功率并没有马上下降
but instead of the power going down immediately,
而是在极短时间内上升了
for a brief moment it went up.
这怎么可能
How is that possible?
我的一位同事沃科夫
Well, this was the very question posed
就提出了这个问题
by a colleague of mine named Volkov.
他是这篇文章的作者
He's the one who wrote this article.
RBMK型反应堆在低功率下运行时
When an RBMK reactor runs at low power,
状态相当不稳定
it's notoriously unstable.
易发生反应性波动
Prone to swings in reactivity.
正常情况下
Under normal circumstances,
控制棒可以弥补这一点
the control rods can compensate for that.
正常情况下
Under normal circumstances.
切尔诺贝利工作人员在测试期间降低了反应堆功率
The Chernobyl staff stalled the reactor during the test.
为了恢复电力  他们几乎把
They pulled almost all the control rods out
所有控制棒都拔出来了
to bring the power back up.
这也是沃科夫在列宁格勒发现的
This is what Volkov learned from Leningrad.
当硼控制棒
If the boron control rods
完全从反应堆中抽出后
are completely withdrawn from the reactor,
再放回去时
when they're put back in,
最先接触堆芯的不是硼
the first thing that enters the core isn't boron.
而是石墨
It's graphite.
控制棒尖端是石墨
The control rods have graphite tips
会置换水和蒸汽
that displace water and steam.
因此反应功率不会降低
So the reactivity doesn't go down.
相反会急剧上升
It goes up dramatically.
他们为什么要按下那个按钮
Why on Earth would they press that button?
他们不知道
They didn't know.
沃尔科夫提醒过克里姆林宫
Volkov warned the Kremlin,
那是十年前了
ten years ago.
但苏联核工业领域的
But there could be no doubt
绝对霸权是不容置疑的
about the supremacy of the Soviet nuclear industry.
克格勃将其列为国家机密
The KGB classified it as a state secret.
当我看到反应堆被炸开时
When I saw the reactor blown open,
我仍不认为会是AZ-5的缺陷导致的
I still didn't think it could be this flaw in AZ-5.
因为这个缺陷不会导致爆炸
Because the flaw will not lead to an explosion
除非操作人员已把反应堆
unless the operators have pushed the reactor
推向了灾难边缘
to the edge of disaster.
-所以是他们的错吗  -是的
- So it is their fault? - Yes.
但不全是他们的错
But not only their fault.
对
No.
你打算在维也纳也这么说吗
Is that what you're going to say in Vienna?
你不会那么天真吧
You can't possibly be that naive.
目前整个苏联有16个
There are 16 RBMK reactors
RBMK型反应堆
running in the Soviet Union right now.
我们必须整改它们
We have to fix them.
唯一的办法就是公开
The only way to do that is to go public,
迫使中央委员会采取行动
force the Central Committee to take action.
你这样做会让列加索夫羞辱一个
What you're proposing is that Legasov humiliate a nation
不能忍受羞辱的国家
that is obsessed with not being humiliated.
我们可以和克格勃谈条件
We can make a deal with the KGB.
你去维也纳时不要提及这事
You'll leave this information out in Vienna,
克格勃会私下让我们修好剩下的反应堆
and they quietly let us fix the remaining reactors.
和克格勃谈条件
A deal with the KGB?
你还说我天真
And I'm "naive."
他们会盯上你的家人  你的朋友
They'll go after your family, they'll go after your friends.
你有机会向全世界发声  瓦列利
You have a chance to talk to the world, Valery.
如果我有这个机会...
If that chance was mine--
但你没有这个机会
But it isn't, is it?
我认识比你更勇敢的人  霍缪克
I've know braver souls than you, Khomyuk.
那些人拥有机会却最终什么都没做
Men who had their moment and did nothing.
因为一旦涉及到你和你所爱的人的生命
Because when it's your life and the lives of everyone you love,
你的道德信念就一文不值了
your moral conviction doesn't mean anything.
会被你抛诸脑后
It leaves you.
到时候你脑中只有不想被枪毙
And all you want at that moment is not to be shot.
你知道瓦西里·伊格纳滕科这个名字吗
Do you know the name Vasily Ignatenko?
不知道
No.
他是一名消防员
He was a fireman.
他在爆炸后两周死去了
He died two weeks after the accident.
我去看望过他的遗孀
I've been looking in on his widow.
她生下了遗腹子
She gave birth.
是一个女孩
A girl.
孩子挣扎了四个小时
The baby lived for four hours.
他们说那个母亲遭受的辐射量原本足以致死
They said the radiation would have killed the mother,
但却被腹中的孩子吸收了
but the baby absorbed it instead.
她的孩子
Her baby.
在我们生活的国家
We live in a country
孩子们要替母亲去死
where children have to die to save their mothers.
去你的条件
To hell with your deal.
管我们会怎样呢
And to hell with our lives.
得有人说出真相
Someone has to start telling the truth.
恭喜各位同志们
Congratulations, comrades.
你们是3828人中的最后一批
You are the last of 3,828 men.
你们出色地履行了自己的职责
You have performed your duties perfectly.
希望你们健康长寿
I wish you good health and long life.
每个人奖励八百卢比
All of you are awarded a bonus of 800 rubles.
-谢谢  -为苏联服务
- Thank you. - I serve the Soviet Union.